So today's דף Daf is officially כ"ז. Chaf-Zayin. We are at the
bottom of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf-Vav Amud Aleph. We pick up with
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, two lines from the bottom, and we're dealing
again with the ability to sell a שול Shul and other parts
of the שול Shul and things related to the ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. And the one initial limitation we had was one more about
who has rights and the question about, it's one thing to sell
it in a village, but something that's in more of a city
might have a global communal ownership, not just of the people of
the city, but of everyone. And then there's a question of really
who has the right to sell it. Now we get back to
the halakhic question about the consequence of selling it or the halakhic,
not so much the ownership or the issue of the right, but
the question of selling, but in terms of, you know, in terms
of what are the ritual limitations and what can be done with
the money. So אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, לא שנו
אלא שלא מכרו שבעה טובי העיר במעמד אנשי העיר. lo shanu ela
shelo machru shiva tuvei ha'ir bemamad anshei ha'ir. These limits, presumably that
you have to use the money for a higher purpose and not
for a lower purpose, is only when it was not sold by
the שבעה טובי העיר, shiva tuvei ha'ir, seven good people of the
city, in the במעמד אנשי העיר, bemamad anshei ha'ir, in the presence
of all the people of the city. So these שבעה טובי העיר,
shiva tuvei ha'ir, seven good people of the city, like upstanding citizens
of the city, these are seen as like, if you would, the
city elders. They are seen as the people that represent the lay
leadership of the city. Okay, there was this concept of שבעה טובי
העיר. shiva tuvei ha'ir. So this represented the lay leadership of the
city. So that's only, those limits apply only when it's not sold
in the, with the elders together with the presence of the whole
city. Like מעמד אנשי העיר mamad anshei ha'ir sort of evokes the
whole story with, you know, what is it, with עפרון, Ephron, you
know, and החתי, Hachitti, and says, you know, באזני באי שער עירו
לאמר, be'oznei boei sha'ar iro lemor, you know, doing a sale in
the presence of everybody in the city. אבל מכרו שבעה טובי העיר
במעמד אנשי העיר, aval machru shiva tuvei ha'ir bemamad anshei ha'ir, so
that's only when it was sold let's say by the, you know,
question of like one or the other. Either by somehow some group
of people of the city without the elders or the elders without
being in the presence of the city. But if it's sold by
the elders in the presence of the city, so it's like you
have the official backing of both the popular vote of the city
and the authorities of the city, and everybody combined or the village
is selling it. In that case, אבל מכרו שבעה טובי העיר במעמד
אנשי העיר, aval machru shiva tuvei ha'ir bemamad anshei ha'ir, in that
case, top of כ"ו עמוד ב', Chaf-Vav Amud Bet, אפילו למשתא ביה
שיכרא שפיר דמי. afilu lemishta bei shichra shapir dami. Even to drink
in it beer is okay. Now there's a big question about the
word למשתא ביה שיכרא, lemishta bei shichra, drink in it or drink
with it? What's the difference? If you say you can even drink
beer in it, then what do you mean? You can drink beer
where? In the synagogue after it was sold? You have completely if
you would desacralized the synagogue and it can be used for any
purpose. If you read if you can drink beer with it, with
what? With the proceeds. So the simple, the initial sense that we're
talking about here because our משנה Mishnah has not yet addressed what
can be done with the synagogue after it's sold and we are
going to see that discussion come up in a later משנה. Mishnah.
The first immediate concern of ours is not what you can do
with the synagogue, but what you can do with the money. So
many ראשונים Rishonim choose to read this גמרא, Gemara, you can drink
with the proceeds money, you can use the money of the proceeds
to buy beer, okay, but some, including רש"י, Rashi, read that you
can even drink beer in the synagogue. That if the elders of
the city together with the whole city are behind the sale, then
it completely desacralizes the synagogue. Okay, now that's an interesting question, what
process do you need to desacralize the synagogue? How exactly does that
occur is, you know, again I'll remind you that according to the
רמב"ם, Rambam, once it's no longer being used for the מצוה, mitzvah,
like a לולב lulav after סוכות, Succos, you can use it for
anything you want, you can even throw it out. So as long
as everybody is behind its changing its status or not using this
anymore, then you can do anything you want, no limits. Okay, so
that is one idea, I want to bracket that because we're going
to get to the issue of what you can do with the
synagogue after it's sold later, and we'll actually see in a later
משנה Mishnah that it might even not require any special circumstances as
a general rule, you might be able to use it for pretty
much anything with a small number of things you can't use which
are considered really like deeply, you know, disgraceful and disrespectful, same way
like you don't, you know, I don't know, you know, before we
throw out our לולב lulav we tend to like wrap it in
something, we don't throw it out with the chicken bones and the
rest of the garbage, okay? So that's going to be a later
משנה. Mishnah. It might be in general you have a lot of
latitude what to do with the synagogue after it's sold. We're going
to focus on what the focus of our משנה, Mishnah, which seems
to be the primary focus of it, of what can you do
with the proceeds? And even there the issue is that the limit
of the proceeds or the transfer of some status of קדושה Kedusha
to the proceeds is only when it is
legally. then somehow it’s like you’re completely free to use the money.
And again, this is an interesting question of conceptually what is the
mechanism going here, because if there’s some mechanism of transfer of קדושה,
Kedushah, then who cares if everybody is behind it? How does the
קדושה Kedushah disappear? Okay, which is again the reason that the רמב"ן
Ramban plays down the idea of classic models of קדושה Kedushah and
speaks primarily about is it respectful to use the money for something
else or not since it was once used for a מצוה. mitzvah.
And if it’s all an issue of is it respectful and proper
and so on, then you can sort of start fudging it under
different circumstances. But this really represents, you know, challenging questions of what
is the whole mechanism. Yes, Michael. But there’s this idea that the
גמרא Gemara had brought up the issue that there are people from
elsewhere. So even if you do it—you no longer deal with people
from elsewhere. Now we’re dealing with a כפר kfar or village. Oh
okay, so back to a village and we’re back to the limits
of the משנה. Mishnah. In a bigger city you couldn’t. Then you
couldn’t sell it to begin with. Yes. In the רמב"ן’s Ramban view
or anyone who is not—is there any decommissioning required? Like if the
building is the same, it’s still there, it’s not—right,
so that’s the funny thing, not the decommissioning, what do they also
call it with a museum, the deaccession or something of the—anyway, when
they sell their paintings. Anyway, the decommissioning comes by this more formal
process that everybody is there as opposed to just, oh you know,
the board officer signed off on it. You get everybody, you get
all of the people to come together and
participate in the sale, you know, במעמד אנשי העיר, b'maamad anshei ha'ir,
that formally sort of completely sort of withdraws the status. But again,
it’s funny exactly what that mechanism is. Let’s keep on going. רבינא
הוה ליה ההוא תילא דבי כנישתא. Ravina hava lei hahu tila d'vei
knishta.
רבינא Ravina had a certain mound of a בי כנישתא, bei knishta,
a collapsed synagogue, and presumably he wanted—question did he own it? Was
he interested in it? Let’s take a look. אתא לקמיה דרבא, ata
lekamei d'Rava, he came to רבא. Rava. אמר ליה רבא amar lei
Rava and he said to רבא, Rava, מהו למיזרע, mahu lemizra, can
I plant on the field? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to
him, זיל זבניה משבעה טובי העיר zil zabneih mi-shivah tuvei ha'ir במעמד
אנשי העיר. b'maamad anshei ha'ir. Go buy it from the seven elders
of the city, so it sounds like he was interested in it.
Okay, he wanted to buy it. So go buy it from the
seven elders of the city במעמד אנשי העיר, b'maamad anshei ha'ir, in
the presence of the people of the city, וזרעא uzra and then
you can plant it. So again, very confusing. It said he had
it, but then it said he wanted to buy it. And again,
this sort of reinforces seems to be רש"י’s Rashi approach that doing
this type of a formal sale with everybody present, you know, the
elders and the people, allows you also a wide range of use
for what you’re going to do with the synagogue itself, and that
that’s a process that allows not just use of the money because
where were we talking about the money here? So again, various ראשונים
Rishonim who want to focus on the money try to reinterpret this
case. But this does sort of reinforce רש"י’s Rashi read that it
gives you opportunity to do what you want with the—yeah, but then
again, why the אנשי העיר, anshei ha'ir, what’s going on here? That
somehow that process also gives you more latitude with what to do
with the synagogue itself. Okay, but keep all in mind because the
question of what to do with the synagogue will come up in
a משנה Mishnah later, which should be today’s דף daf if we
get there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara continues. רמי בר אבא הוה
קבני בי כנישתא. Rami bar Abba hava kabani bei knishta.
רמי בר אבא Rami bar Abba was building a synagogue. הוה האי
כנישתא
עתיקתא, hava hei knishta atikta, and there was an old synagogue. הוה
בעי למיסתריה ולאתויי ליבני וכשורי
מיניה. hava ba'ei lemistrei u-le'asuyei livnei ve-kashurei minei. So he had a
great idea. Let’s knock down that old synagogue that nobody is דאווענינג
davening in anyway and let’s go ahead and use the beams and
the stones and use them to rebuild this synagogue, to build this
synagogue. Right? Why pay for more raw materials? ואתויי להכא v'ayuwei lehakha
and bring it here. יתיב וקמיבעיא ליה. yativ ve-ka mibaya lei. So
he was sitting and he was sort of pondering the following question.
הא דרב חסדא, hada d'Rav Chisda, the statement of רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. דאמר רב חסדא d'amar Rav Chisda because רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, לא ליסתרי בי כנישתא עד דבני
בי כנישתא אחריתי. lo listrei bei knishta ad d'bani bei knishta achriti.
People should not knock down one synagogue until they build another synagogue.
So why not? התם משום פשיעותא. hatam mishum peshiuta.
That’s because you’re afraid people will be negligent. They’ll knock down the
first synagogue and then they’ll never get around to building the next
one and they’ll be without a synagogue and it also
won’t be respectful that this was knocked down and it wasn’t used
for the other, you know, for the other one. So that was
the concern. So if that’s true, כי האי גוונא מאי? ki hai
gavna mai? What about this case? You’re already in the process of
building the second synagogue, so there’s no concern that it’s going to
be—you’re going to be negligent. You’re going to knock down and שלעפּ
schlepp it here. You’ve got plans to build a synagogue, you’re in
the middle of building the other synagogue. So אתא לקמיה דרב פפא,
ata lekamei d'Rav Pappa, he came to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, ואסרה
ליה v'asra lei and רב פפא Rav Pappa said no, I’m sorry,
it’s still forbidden. לקמיה דרב הונא ואסרה ליה, lekamei d'Rav Huna v'asra
lei, he came to רב הונא Rav Huna and he made it
forbidden. How can you פסקן posken shop? I don’t know. Well, that’s
a good question. That is a good question. What’s he doing, keeping
on asking other people? Maybe he was asking hypothetically. Okay, but you’re
right, ואסרה ליה v'asra lei made it forbidden to him. It’s a
good question, right? How could he go to someone else? אמר רב,
amar Rav, now the גמרא Gemara doesn’t sort of tell us why
not. Is it a type of a לא פלוג? lo plug? Is
it somehow an issue that’s not just משום פשיעותא? mishum peshiuta? Is
it also because of a question of like disrespect, you know, to
Maybe it has to be sold in order to allow it then
to be knocked down. It's not clear. We're going to have another
story right here that's also going to deal with a similar issue
about what's the story about it before it's been sold. Okay, because
again, even if the sale, until now we've been focused what can
you do with the proceeds, but I've been telling you that when
you once you've sold it, the synagogue itself might be able to
be used for a wide range of purposes, particularly if you sold
it with מעמד אנשי העיר, ma'amad anshei ha'ir, but maybe even not.
Maybe once you sold it it's fine. But how about if it
hasn't yet been sold? So this scenario is, it hasn't been sold,
it's defunct, it's break, it's falling down, but it hasn't been sold.
Maybe you're still somewhat restricted. Let's take a look at the next
case about something similar about that. What? You didn't talk before about
it, demolishing the synagogue to rebuild it on the same place. Ah,
that's a good question and I definitely, yes, that does get discussed
because then even if you said there was some issue about, you
know, about it sort of respecting it in its current status and
so on, it's like it's all in the process of building it,
it's not in the process of just destroying it. So that's a
good point. Yeah. I don't understand, how is, if it's not sold,
how is he able to just use the beams unless he's stealing?
What? He can't just, let's say he owns both of them. But
the point is, you know, or the city owns both of them
and the city is building the second one. They're not stealing. It's
not a question of ownership, but the question of its status as
a synagogue. As long as you haven't sold it, even if you
own it, it still has a status of a synagogue. That, that
might be the issue, right? So you can't destroy a synagogue even
if you're going to, now again this also gets to the question,
I'll remind you, of the משנה Mishnah of starting that you have
to use something that you do sell for a higher purpose. Here
it's being used for, or that's the question, is it used for
a higher or don't use it for a lower? Here it's being
used for the same purpose. But also it's not just being sold
and its proceeds, it's actually destroying it. So as long as it's
a synagogue even if it's yours, you might be limited. Okay, or
it could just be a לא פלוג lo plug of פשיעותא p'shisuta
concerning negligence. You didn't build the other one, but you
didn't even need to sell it, you can still destroy it. What?
It implies they've already built the other one, right? Mean you couldn't
destroy it. No, because the first one is still a synagogue. Until
you sold it maybe it's still a synagogue. עד דבנא, ad d'bana,
doesn't it say עד דבנא? ad d'bana?
Oh, עד דבנא. ad d'bana. That's an interesting question. Okay, does does
the very fact that you've created a replacement somehow shift maybe that's
interesting. Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't explain why. And maybe it
still is משום פשיעותא. mishum p'shisuta. Let's take a look. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, says Rava, האי בי כנישתא, hai bei knishta, if
you have a synagogue, חלופה וזבונה שרי. chalufa u'zvuna shari. If you
exchange it, okay, so basically it's like, you know, this happens, right,
a property swap, you know, I'll take your building and use that
for a synagogue, you take my building, you'll knock it down and
build some high-rise or something. Once you've exchanged it, fine. That's or
certainly selling it, that's permissible because now it's no longer a synagogue.
It's been sold, it's been exchanged, an exchange is a form of
sale. Now it what again, not what the proceeds, you can do
with the synagogue whatever you want, it lost its status. Okay, that's
fine. שפיר שרי. Shapir shari. אוגורה אוגורה ומשכונה, Ogura ogura u'mashkona, to
rent it or to use it as collateral, so it's still a
synagogue. It hasn't been sold, right? So if there's no sale then
and you want to rent it out, rent out my synagogue so
people can use it as a youth hostel, that's forbidden, אסור. asur.
It's still a synagogue. So it needs to be sold in order
for its status to change. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why? בקדושתה קאי,
B'kdushatah kai, it still retains its sanctity until it's been sold its
status remains. Okay. Isn't that still seeing it as part of it,
Miller was saying still use it as synagogue and use part of
it as youth hostel. What? Can you use half of it as
youth hostel?
Yeah, that's question about על תנאי, al t'nai, הינא סיין, hina sayan,
let's not go into that. לבני נמי, Livnei nami, by the bricks
as well, let's say you've got bricks that you've set aside for
building the synagogue, חלופין וזבוני שרי, chalufin u'zvuni shari, to sell the
bricks or you exchange them, then they are desanctified, they can be
used for whatever they need to be. אזפונהו, Azfun'hu, if you if
you lent out the bricks, I don't know what it means to
lend a brick but okay, אסור, asur, it's forbidden. הני מילי, Hani
mili, that is only בעתיקתא, b'atikta, old bricks like the previous case,
the synagogue was falling down and there were some even some bricks
that already dislodged. So there it still retains its status until it's
sold.
אבל בחדתא, Aval b'chadta, you've just been piling up bricks and bought
bricks to build the synagogue, you haven't built them into the synagogue
yet, לית לן בה, leit lan bah, then there's no sanctity. The
fact that you brought them for that purpose and planning to use
them does not give it sanctity until it's actually been built into
and used as the synagogue. ואפילו, Ve'afilu, and now this gets into
a larger conceptual issue, ואפילו מאן דאמר הזמנה מילתא היא, ve'afilu man
d'amar hazmanah milta hi, even according to the opinion that designating is
significant even before it's used and it gives something a status, הני
מילי כגון דאורג בגד למת, hani mili k'gon d'oreg beged l'meit, that's
for example if somebody goes ahead and weaves a shroud for a
corpse, so even before it's placed on the dead body, according to
one opinion, if it's woven and made for that for the corpse,
it has a status of shrouds and you cannot get benefit. That's
okay, but that's when it's completely already like fit to be used.
אבל הכא כטוויה לאריג דמי, Aval hacha ketavya le'arig dami, here it's
not like the garment's been woven, here it's like you spun the
thread, okay, so just buying bricks is not yet, right, you know,
you know, would be parallel to weaving a garment for the body
and not putting it on the body would be building the synagogue
and not having used it yet. So you built it, you didn't
use it yet, does it have its status before it's actually been
used? You made the garments, he hasn't been put on the dead
body, do they have status of shrouds yet? That is the debate
of
הזמנה מילתא. Hazmana milta. But just but just, you know, having the
bricks and not yet the synagogue, that's too far removed and that
designation has no significance and they and they have no status according
to everyone. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
מתנה, Matana, now let's say giving the building as a gift, okay,
would giving the building as a gift de-sanctify it? Because we spoke
about exchanging and selling, what about gifting the building? Okay, פליגי רב
אחא ורבינא, Pligi Rav Acha u'Ravina, Rav Acha and Ravina debated it.
חד אסר וחד שרי, Chad asar ve'chad sharei, one forbade it, one
permitted it. מאן דאסר, Man de'asar, the one who forbade it said,
בהי תיפקע קדושתיה, Behai tifka kedushateih, in what mechanism is the קדושה
kedusha going to be removed? There's no money, there's no object that
it's exchanged for, so if you think about normal concepts of קדושה,
kedusha, קדושה kedusha doesn't disappear, it has to be transferred. So if
there's a sale or exchange, it's transferred; as a gift, what's it
transferred on? So very reasonable point. ומאן דשרי, U'man de'sharei, the one
who permitted it said, אי לאו דהוה ליה הנאה מיניה, Ei lav
de'havah leh hana'ah mineih, if why are you giving somebody a gift
unless in the past, you know, you had received some type of
a benefit from this person, לא הוה יהיב ליה, lo havah yahiv
leh, you would not be giving them a gift now. So therefore
there is a form of exchange. Now again the Ramban says there
might be a form of exchange in some sense of that it's,
you know, reciprocal, but if you need a mechanism to transfer קדושה,
kedusha, just because a year ago you lent me your lawnmower, you
were nice to me and you helped me out, it doesn't explain
where that קדושה's kedusha going when I give you this synagogue. What's
the thing it's being transferred to? So again there is a huge
problem here of classic mechanisms, which is why the Ramban makes it
very much not about קדושה kedusha at all and sort of avoiding
the whole language here, and others want to say, okay, if the
קדושה, kedusha, but it's more of a rabbinic קדושה kedusha and we
could be a little bit more flexible with the mechanisms. So one
issue is the de-sanctifying of the synagogue, does it need some object
of money, of value, of concrete to transfer the קדושה kedusha to?
And the other challenging mechanism is that when it's sold by שבעה
טובי העיר shiva tuvei ha'ir by the whole city and the leaders
of the city, how come the money doesn't become sanctified? Then you
really say, well where did the קדושה kedusha go? It left the
synagogue and it didn't go onto the money, and we can use
the money for whatever we want. So there are definitely times where
it's hard to explain the mechanism, which is why the ראשונים Rishonim
really grapple with what is the appropriate model to apply here. Yeah,
there's an issue of תפיסת קדושה tefisat kedusha and this should apply
even if it's the townspeople, not במעמד אנשי העיר, ma'amad anshei ha'ir,
because it has to get the קדושה kedusha on it. That's exactly
what I just said and therefore you can't understand why במעמד אנשי
העיר ma'amad anshei ha'ir works. So that's why everybody has to say
either it is a קדושה kedusha model but we have a very
flexible mechanisms, and you know, or the Ramban tries to avoid the
whole real real idea of קדושה kedusha here in the classic sense.
Okay, because the mechanisms do not work as they classically do. No
more. We have to go. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Now the גמרא
Gemara intro-thing and this is nice for the Ramban because this is
exactly the category Ramban wants to put this in, which is תשמישי
מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah, not real קדושה. kedusha. So here a ברייתא Braisa
is introduced about תשמישי מצוה. tashmishei mitzvah. תשמישי מצוה, Tashmishei mitzvah, objects
used, מצוה mitzvah objects, נזרקין, nizrakin, can be thrown out after you're
done with them, which is how the Ramban tries to understand the
synagogue. תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei kedusha, objects used that are associated with קדושה,
kedusha, holiness, which basically means כתבי קודש kisvei kodesh and שם השם,
shem Hashem, okay, now that would actually be considered
the חפצא cheftza itself, an object of קדושה. kedusha. תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei
kedusha are things that are used in association with a ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. Okay, we'll see what they are in a minute. Those
types of things נגנזין, nignazin,
even when you're done with them you have to bury them. Okay,
you put it into שמות. sheimos. Or sell? Not sell them, no,
no. Only a synagogue can you sell. Things that have intrinsic קדושה
kedusha like this, you know, their status remains even when you're done
with them. ואלו הן תשמישי מצוה, Ve'eilu hein tashmishei mitzvah, these is
objects of things used for a מצוה, mitzvah, סוכה לולב שופר ציצית,
sukkah, lulav, shofar, tzitzit, and you're done with it, you know, you
could throw it out. You don't you're not נוהג בו מנהג בזיון,
noheg bo minhag bizayon, a way of showing disrespect, but you can
discard it. Okay, ואלו הן תשמישי קדושה, Ve'eilu hein tashmishei kedusha, things
these are things that are used for קדושה, kedusha, דלוסקמי deluskami which
which is a ספרים sefarim which is like a type of a
sack that you put scrolls in, תפילין ומזוזות, tefillin u'mezuzot, you have
the תפילין tefillin and מזוזות mezuzot which are used to house, I
mean the תפילין tefillin house the actual קלף. klaf.
The מזוזות mezuzos is interesting because מזוזות mezuzos normally refers to the
scroll itself, so it could be that the גמרא Gemara here is
actually
talking about
how does it translate by the way, דלוסקמי ספרי, dluska'mi sfarim, does
it translate that as one thing or two things?
דלוסקמי ספרי. dluska'mi sfarim. ספרי, sfarim, which is what I said, sacks
of ספרי. sfarim. Yeah, but it is interesting that it mentions the
מזוזה mezuzah because the מזוזה mezuzah is
itself... דלוסקמי ספרי dluska'mi sfarim too. Oh, that's how we read it.
Oh, okay fine, I got it, I got it, okay fine, okay.
Because the תפילין tefillin you could say the בתים battim as opposed
to the whatever as opposed to the actual scrolls in it because
the scrolls themselves and שם השם Shem Hashem is considered קדושה kedusha
itself. Okay, so דלוסקמי ספרי תפילין ומזוזות, dluska'mi sfarim tefillin u'mezuzos, so
sacks that are used for ספרי תפילין ומזוזות, sfarim tefillin u'mezuzos, the
תיק של ספר תורה, tik shel sefer Torah, the mantle of the
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, the נרתיק של תפילין nartik shel tefillin or
the bag for
תפילין, tefillin, ורצועותיהן, ve'retzuoteihen, and the actual רצועות retzuot of the תפילין.
tefillin. So all these things are directly associated with the תפילין, tefillin,
you know, and the מזוזות mezuzos and the ספר תורה sefer Torah
themselves. Now, אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, מריש הוה אמינא,
Me'reish hava amina, I initially used to say, האי כורסייא תשמיש דתשמיש
הוא ושרי. Hai korsaya tashmish de'tashmish hu ve'shari.
A כורסייא korsaya which רש״י Rashi says is the בימה, bimah, right,
our, you know, our בימה, bimah, is a תשמיש tashmish of a
תשמיש, tashmish, two degrees removed. Because it serves the cover that you
put on it and the cover is the one that's directly in
contact with the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, so it's two degrees removed
from the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. כיון דחזינא דמותבי ליה ספר תורה,
Keivan de'hazina de'mosvei lei sefer Torah,
since I see sometimes they put a ספר תורה sefer Torah directly
on it without putting a cover on the בימה, bimah, so אמינא
תשמיש קדושה הוא ואסור. amina tashmish kedusha hu ve'asar. It's a direct
תשמיש קדושה. tashmish kedusha. Interesting, even though it's only presumably an occasional
time that it's used that way. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, and רבא
Rava used to say, מריש הוה אמינא Me'reish hava amina I used
to say, האי פריסא תשמיש דתשמיש הוא, Hai prisa tashmish de'tashmish hu,
that the פריסא, prisa, which is the
curtain that we put in front of the ארון, aron, is a
תשמיש tashmish of a תשמיש. tashmish. The ארון aron serves the ספר
תורה sefer Torah and the curtain serves the ארון. aron. כיון דחזינא
דעייפי ליה ומנחי סיפרא עליה, Keivan de'hazina de'aifilei u'manchi sifa lei, since
I see that sometimes they wrap it and they put the ספר
תורה sefer Torah directly on it, that sometimes they I don't know
they remove the cover or they use the cover to directly you
know wrap the ספר תורה sefer Torah around or wrap around the
ספר תורה, sefer Torah,
or put beneath the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, אמינא תשמיש קדושה הוא
ואסור. amina tashmish kedusha hu ve'asar. It's a תשמיש קדושה tashmish kedusha
and it's forbidden. So again notice all the תשמישי קדושה tashmishey kedusha
are directly associated with ספר תורה, sefer Torah, תפילין tefillin and מזוזות.
mezuzos. And then again this raises the question of what are we
saying about the synagogue? Is a synagogue קדושה kedusha or מצוה? mitzvah?
And that's exactly into that gap sort of is where because a
synagogue also has a ספר תורה sefer Torah and there's also דברים
שבקדושה, devarim she'bi'kdusha, but there's also תפילה. tefillah. So that's sort of,
it's funny the גמרא Gemara plops this down here and that sort
of is where into that gap goes the רמב״ן Ramban and says
we're talking about that the synagogue is דוקא davka not תשמישי קדושה.
tashmishey kedusha. Okay, ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, מריש הוה אמינא, me'reish hava
amina, I just did that. Okay. ואסור. Ve'asar. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava,
רבא Rava also says, האי תיבותא דאירפית, Hai teivusa de'irfat,
if you have a certain ark that is you know ארון aron
that is falling apart, okay, נעבדיה תיבה זוטרתי שרי כורסייא אסור. na'avdeh
teiva zutrati shari korsaya asar.
If you want to take it apart and make it into a
smaller ark because you can't make the same size I guess because
it's falling apart, that's okay. But if you want to make it
into a בימה, bimah, that's not okay because a בימה bimah is
a lower level. Right, a בימה bimah is sometimes two degrees removed,
the ark directly houses the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, etc. Now of
course the problem here is how is this exactly different from the
שול shul that is falling apart, you know, and so on. This
might be what דוב Dov is talking about about building another שול
shul in the same place. Okay, you're salvaging it, you're maintaining it,
you know, by rebuilding it as a smaller one.
ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, and רבא Rava also said, האי
פריסא דבלא, Hai prisa de'vala, if you have a curtain that has
been worn away, right, like a curtain in front of the
ארון, aron, למיעבד פריסא לספרי שרי. le'meivdei prisa le'safrei shari. If you
want to go ahead and to use it to be some type
of a wrap and a cover for ספרי, sfarim, you know, that
is permissible for
ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, because again you're still using it directly for
a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, not as a cover to the ארון,
aron, but as a cover for the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. That's
okay. But לחומשי אסור. le'humashei asar. If you want to use it
just for a חומש, Chumash, it's forbidden. Now what's a חומש Chumash
as opposed to a ספר תורה? sefer Torah? So we might be
inclined to say that a חומש Chumash is more of a codex
than a ספר תורה sefer Torah which is a scroll. רש״י Rashi
says that a חומש, Chumash, no, means actually a single one of
the five חמשה חומשי תורה. hamishey humshei Torah. It is a scroll.
Right, I don't know, somebody can tell us when exactly they started
having codexes, but I do not think it was in this period.
I think it was a few hundreds of years later, right, that
the first codex existed. Right, people know what a codex is, right?
Do you know what a codex is? It's structured like a book,
but every page but it's not printed, every page is scribed. Okay,
but the benefit of a codex is its random access. You don't
have to scroll, right? Okay, but anyway, but here חומש Chumash means
an individual Torah scroll, an individual one of the five books of
the Torah, not the entire Torah. So that is a lower level
of קדושה Kedusha and therefore that would be forbidden. Okay,
where were we? ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, Rava also said, הני זבילי
דחומשי hani zvilei dechumshi וכמטרי דספרי v'kamtarei desifrei
תשמיש קדושה נינהו. tashmish kedusha nin-hu. So the, let me just check
רש"י Rashi here. זבילי Zvilei is right. Oh, so bags. Okay, so
various bags of for חומשים, Chumashim, I mean again חומשים Chumashim means
individual volumes, individual scrolls, and I lost my place here. Okay, and
boxes used for ספרים Sefarim are תשמיש קדושה Tashmish Kedusha ונגנזים v'nignazim
and if they get worn out you have to bury them. פשיטא,
Pshita, obviously, right? You just said that before. Of course you use
them. No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought הני לאו
לכבודא עבידי. hani lav lichvuda avidi. These are not things that are
done to hold them in a place of honor like you think
about an ארון, Aron, it's a way of storing it that shows,
you know, that shows respect to it. But maybe these are just
like, you know, these are just like footlockers. You know, yes they're
used but they're used for storage. They're not used, you store them
there but it's not a place that you place them for honor.
So הני לאו לכבודא עבידי, hani lav lichvuda avidi, לנטורי בעלמא עבידי,
l'naturei b'alma avidi,
just to protect them. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. So קא
משמע לן Ka mashma lan preserves and re-brings that even if it
is only לנטורי בעלמא, l'naturei b'alma, it's still תשמיש קדושה. Tashmish Kedusha.
Yes? Codex largely replaced the scroll by the sixth or seventh century.
Oh, sixth or seventh century, so not too long after the גמרא
Gemara was done. Okay, but start appearing as early as the second
century Roman times. Oh, so wait, so they existed in Roman times
already a codex? As far as codexes are often associated with the
rise of Christianity. Oh, so there were codexes in the time of
the גמרא. Gemara. So that's interesting. So I don't know if anybody
suggests that that's what the חומש Chumash is in the גמרא. Gemara.
רש"י Rashi says חומש Chumash is an individual scroll. Okay, it's I
wonder I do wonder if people might suggest that the other thing.
Yes? So if this connects to קדושה Kedusha on the on the
בית הכנסת? Beis Haknesses? Yes. It seems as other things we have
here are related to שמות. Shemos. Yes. Right. Is the בית הכנסת?
Beis Haknesses? You mean שם השם. Shem Hashem. Right, right. Right, not
your name or mine. Right. Or not שמות shemos that you put
in גניזה. Genizah. Yes, okay, yes, which is where... Is the בית
הכנסת Beis Haknesses there also as a receptacle for the holy script?
Yes, so that's what I read when we read the first משנה,
Mishna, that you could read the first משנה Mishna as everything is
related to the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, right? And the whole idea
of the רחוב Rechov even is not just that you would דאוון
davven in the רחוב Rechov but you would bring the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah into the רחוב. Rechov. So you could read all of
this as a type of extended תשמיש קדושה, tashmish kedusha, right? And
all based on that model, right? Or you could read it as
no, everything about the ספר תורה Sefer Torah is תשמיש קדושה tashmish
kedusha and the בית הכנסת Beis Haknesses is about תפילה. Tefilla. Okay,
so I think that that's exactly this ambiguity that's going on. It's
exactly that. And I think the language we would use today is
community facility. Oh, well, that's that's that's that's what בית כנסת Beis
Kenesses is exactly sort of what it means is a gathering place
as well, but you know, but תפילה, Tefilla, community facility would not
give קדושה kedusha I think in the eyes of the rabbis. Right,
for many many uses but the fact that the community is gathered
there for תפילה. tefilla. Right, as opposed to a private place for
תפילה. tefilla. Right, exactly, exactly. Okay, which then becomes the issue that
the קדושה kedusha is דברים שבקדושה devarim shebakdusha that is said in
תפילה, tefilla, which is that other approach. Right. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. ההוא בי כנישתא דרומאי, Hahu bei knishta deromai,
now of course Jews, but דרומאי deromai for the Roman Jews. Okay,
now what does it mean for the Roman Jews? Was this in
Rome? So רש"י Rashi says it was in בבל Bavel but it
was from people that came from Rome and they built their own
synagogue, which is things that we know throughout history, right? When people
came from different communities or whatever and they had the, you know,
their synagogue for from their you know for for their countrymen. So.
מה דמתא רומי. Me'mata Romi. Exactly, there you go. So this the
Jews the Roman Jewish synagogue דהוה פתיח להו אידרונא, d'hava patiach lehu
idrona, which was open up into a certain room דהוה מנח ביה
מת, d'hava manach bei meis, and a dead body was in it.
Now presumably maybe they would use that room, רש"י Rashi says, you
know to prepare dead bodies for burial and
so on. Okay, but there was a door there was an opening
from one to the other. We've got a problem. והוו בעו כהני
למיעל לצלויי התם. v'havu ba'u kohanei lemei'al litzloyei hatam. The כהנים Kohanim
wanted to go דאוון davven in the שול. shul. And they didn't
want to go to any of the other שול. shuls. They wanted
to go to the Roman one, that's where they came from. Okay,
but the problem is there's a dead body in the next room.
So אמרו ליה לרבא, amru lei l'Rava, they said to Rava, "What
are you going to do?" אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to
them, דלו תיבותא ואותבוה, dalu teivusa v'osvuha, "Take the ארון, Aron, take
the ark, and place it," right, and they didn't have a door,
"and place it in the doorway," דהוה ליה d'hava lei in the
doorway that opens to the other room, כלי עץ העשוי לנחת, kli
etz ha'asuy l'nachas, because it's a wooden vessel that is made for
staying in its place. It's not something that's moved around. וכלי העשוי
לנחת v'kli ha'asui lenachas because it's a wooden vessel that is made
for staying in its place, it's not something that's moved around. וכלי
העשוי לנחת, v'kli ha'asui lenachas, a wooden vessel made for staying in
its place, אינו מקבל טומאה eino mikabel tumah cannot become טמא, tamei,
and if it can't become טמא, tamei, it can be וחוצץ לפני
הטומאה; v'chotzetz lifnei hatumah; it's a barrier and it'll prevent the טומאה
tumah from coming from the other room. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא, amru
lei rabanan l'Rava, the
presumably not, the rabbis said to Rava, והא זימנין דמטלטלי ליה v'ha
zimnin demitalteli lei כי מנח ספר תורה ki manach sefer torah בגויה.
b'gavieh.
So one minute, they said, but it's not that we don't just
put it in one place and leave it there. Sometimes we move
it around, even when a ספר תורה sefer torah is in it.
והא הוי מטלטל מלא וריקם, v'ha havei mitaltel malei v'reikam, and it's
a vessel that's moved not only when it's empty, but even when
it's full. And that's exactly the opposite of something that is made
for staying in its place. So the rabbi says, אי הכי לא
אפשר, ei hachi lo efshar, that's it, you're stuck. Which is the
end of that story. All right, so, but by the way, it's
interesting in that it reflects this issue about a portable ארון aron
and you know, this is interesting also things that archaeologists have found
about various synagogues and so on. You know, wood ארון, aron, was
it fixed, was it built in, or was it portable and so
on. Okay,
yeah, so that's what Michael's asking. So presumably, you know, I mean
the argument is, you know, we're just placing it there, that's where
we decided its place was. I mean, you know, it's not totally
saying this only, this is what it is, it's a block, whatever,
just choose to place your ארון aron there. I don't know, but
you're right, it's a good question. Not in front of the דבבא,
dbava, in the doorway, in the doorway. All right. Anyway, but it's
a good question exactly, you know, when do you, how do you
frame exactly what's respectable. אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, מטפחות ספרים
שבלו mitpachot sefarim shebalu עושים אותם תכריכין למת osim otam tachrichin l'meit
מצוה mitzvah וזו היא גניזתן. v'zu hi genizatan. So you have now
things that were used, wraps that were used for ספרים, sefarim, either
ספרי תורה sifrei torah or ספרי תנ״ך, sifrei Tanach, and they're worn
out, and you can't use them for anything else. So what's the
הלכה? halacha? You have to bury them. We learned that תשמישי קדושה.
tashmishei kedusha. So he says, you know what you should do for
them? Use, turn them into shrouds. Since you have to bury them
anyway, this will be how you bury them. Okay, so you don't
have to get to an argument of is it מעלין בקודש ma'alin
bakodesh or not מעלין בקודש. ma'alin bakodesh. You know, this is, you
could actually just frame it as a form of burying them and
get to use them for a מצוה. mitzvah. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava,
ספר תורה שבלה, sefer torah shebala, you have a ספר תורה sefer
torah that's worn out, you know, and that obviously can no longer
be used, גונזים אותו אצל תלמיד חכם. gonzim oto etzel talmid chacham.
You bury it near a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham in the... I
don't know. ואפילו שונה הלכות, va'afilu shonei halachot, even if he's not
a real תלמיד חכם talmid chacham like he really knows how to
analyze and has a good גמרא קאפ, Gemara kup, he's just like
memorized a lot of הלכות, halachot, right, a lot of like teaching,
הלכות halachot are like short apodictic teachings. Even so, it's respectful, you
know, to bury the physical תורה torah by somebody that represented תורה.
torah. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, ובכלי
חרס. uvichli cheres. And you should bury it in a pottery vessel,
שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says, ונתתם בכלי חרס למען יעמדו ימים רבים.
unatatam bichli cheres lema'an ya'amdu yamim rabim. Put it in a pottery
vessel so it should stay for many years. So you might think
that what we want to do when we bury a ספר תורה
sefer torah is that it should, you know, dissolve, right? But actually
no, the idea is that you should do whatever you can to
preserve it, you know,
I don't think so, I don't know, it's a good question. When
they found the Dead Sea Scrolls, right, they were in pottery vessels,
right? Yeah, but I think it also helped that the desert was
very dry and whatever. Okay, אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav
Pappa mishmei d'Rava, מבי כנישתא לבי רבנן. mibei knishta l'bei rabanan. Now
we get to an old theme that we've heard before. Use which
is a higher קדושה, kedusha, synagogue or study hall? So we just
talked about a ספר תורה sefer torah and a תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, right? Is it the physical תורה torah or is it the
learning of the תורה? torah? Okay, this also though raises the question,
is the בית כנסת beit knesset because of its association to the
physical תורה? torah? So then it would be physical תורה torah or
תלמוד תורה. talmud torah. Or is the בית כנסת beit knesset because
of תפילה? tefillah? And then it's about the whole תפילה tefillah versus
תורה, torah, which is a major theme in ברכות, Berachot, right? Synagogue
versus study hall. So מבי כנישתא לבי רבנן, mibei knishta l'bei rabanan,
to turn something from a synagogue into a rabbi's house study house,
meaning a בית מדרש, beit midrash, שרי, shari, that's permissible. That's going
up in קדושה. kedusha. Even if there's no Torah in it. Yeah.
מבי רבנן לבי כנישתא, mibei rabanan l'bei knishta, the other way, a
בית מדרש beit midrash to a בית כנסת, beit knesset, אסור assur
is forbidden. Not something surprising coming from one of the rabbis. But
now let's see what רב פפא Rav Pappa says. רב פפא משמיה
דרבא אמר, Rav Pappa mishmei d'Rava amar, מתני איפכא, masni ipcha, teaches
the
opposite. So that you can actually... בית כנסת beit knesset has higher
קדושה. kedusha. אמר רב אחא, Amar Rav Acha, כוותיה דרב פפא מסתברא.
kevateih d'Rav Pappa mistabra. Makes sense like רב פפא Rav Pappa that
a בית המדרש beit hamidrash has higher קדושה. kedusha. דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, בית הכנסת מותר לעשותו בית
המדרש. beit haknesset mutar la'asoto beit hamidrash. You can make a בית
הכנסת beit haknesset into a בית מדרש, beit midrash, so straight statement
that supports that. שמע מינה. shma mina. It's a good point. דרש
בר קפרא, Darash Bar Kappara, מאי דכתיב, mai d'ichtiv, what's meant by
the verse? Verse here in the spirit of
תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. וישרף את בית ה׳ ואת בית המלך ואת
כל בתי ירושלים ואת כל בית גדול שרף באש. v'yisrof et beit
Hashem v'et beit hamelech v'et kol batei Yerushalayim v'et kol beit gadol
saraf ba'esh. This is נבוזראדן, Nebuzaradan, the general that came in of
נבוכדנצר, Nebuchadnezzar, came in and he burned everything down and when they
were destroying the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So בית ה׳ Beit Hashem
is the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. בית המלך, Beit Hamelech, the king's
house, אלו פלטרין של מלך, elu paltarin shel melech, palace. ואת כל
בתי ירושלים, v'et kol batei Yerushalayim, כמשמען, kemashma'an, all the houses of
Jerusalem. ואת כל בית גדול, v'et kol beit gadol, what's every great
house? ואת כל בית גדול, ve'et kol bayit gadol, what's every great
house, שרף באש, saraf ba'esh, רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi
Yochanan veRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, there's a debate. חד אמר, chad amar,
מקום שמגדלין בו תורה, makom shemegadlin bo Torah,
it's great because there's that's where תורה Torah increases and grows. It's
a בית מדרש. Beit Medrash. וחד אמר, vechad amar, מקום שמגדלין בו
תפילה, makom shemegadlin bo tefillah, no, it's a place where there's an
enormous where תפילה tefillah is, you know, growing there and increases. מאן
דאמר, man de'amar, and it's great because of prayer. מאן דאמר man
de'amar תורה, Torah, דכתיב, dechativ, and we know תורה Torah is associated
with גדולה gedulah because it says, ה' חפץ למען צדקו יגדיל תורה
ויאדיר. Hashem chafetz lema'an tzidko yagdil Torah veya'adir. תורה Torah should be
יגדיל, yagdil, made very great. So, it's a place, so a בית
גדול bayit gadol is a place of תורה Torah where תורה Torah
is made great. ומאן דאמר uman de'amar תפילה, tefillah, דכתיב, dechativ, and
the one who says תפילה, tefillah, ספרה נא הגדולות אשר עשה אלישע.
saprah na hagedolot asher asah Elisha. Speak about the great deeds that
אלישע Elisha did. Now, אלישע Elisha wasn't a רבי, Rabbi, he wasn't
a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. אלישע דעבד, Elisha de'avad, what did, what
did, how did
אלישע Elisha do his great deed? ברחמי דעבד berachamei de'avad through תפילה.
tefillah. So תפילה tefillah achieves great deeds. So here you have a
dispute. It says what is a great house? Is the great house
the synagogue, or is it the בית המדרש? Beit HaMidrash? Fascinating. So,
תסתיים tistayim דרבי יהושע בן לוי deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi הוא דאמר
hu de'amar מקום שמגדלין בו תורה. makom shemegadlin bo Torah. Let's conclude
that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is the one
that says it's the place of תורה, Torah, that he gives the
תורה, Torah, a בית, bayit, a house of תורה Torah greater status.
דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, because we
just quoted earlier that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
said, הוא דאמר, hu de'amar, בית הכנסת מותר לעשותו בית המדרש, beit
hakeneset mutar la'asoto beit hamedrash, that you can go from a, transfer,
you know, change a שול shul into a בית מדרש. Beit Medrash.
So you see a בית מדרש Beit Medrash is of a higher
status. שמע מינה, shma minah, that is a very good point. So
I have to tell you, to me what's fascinating is the rabbis
who themselves, their accomplishment was in the field of תורה, Torah, that
you still had some of them that said a בית כנסת beit
knesset was a greater place. So, you know, I really do find
that fascinating. Maybe it's because the בית מדרש Beit Medrash also had
a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, so it still was not just about
תפילה tefillah versus. But here it's not mentioned, here it's talked about
מגדלין בו תפילה. megadlin bo tefillah. Really sort of, you know, puts
תפילה tefillah in opposition to תורה, Torah, and you have some of
the ones who represent תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah saying, you know, but
a בית תפילה beit tefillah is even of greater status. So it's
quite fascinating. Now, you could try to, you know, finesse that and
say it doesn't mean תפילה tefillah is greater than תורה, Torah, but
you know, again, what תפילה tefillah has, it has the sense of
תפילת רבים, tefillat rabbim, right, תפילה בציבור. tefillah betzibur. And even though
of course we know, whole idea ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, hundreds of
people learning תורה Torah and so on and the power of תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah etc., there is not, you know, maybe there's some
different status to that idea of like the community places. You're also
saying a community house, but you know, something that is really communal
prayer as opposed to something which is sort of, you know, less
has that recognized communal status to it. And certainly it's a, תפילה
tefillah is more for the entire community whereas תורה Torah is more
for the select few. So it is still though fascinating, you know,
that there's some rabbis that are actually giving greater weight to the
synagogue over the בית המדרש. Beit HaMidrash. Okay, yes, off the top
of my head, I don't know why. Right. Right. You know, we,
we understand that the rabbis tried to supplant the actions of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash with תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Right. But also
organically there was the idea of בית כנסת, beit knesset, which was
not a substitute of a בית המדרש, Beit HaMidrash, right. And so
once that became established, you know, that there's really no reason perhaps
for them to favor one over the other. The basic idea was
how are we going to survive without a בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So these are two options. Right. Right. Maybe. I, right, I hear.
I also what I would sort of add to reinforce that is
that the בית המ... Beit Ha... meaning, you know, the thing I
said before to me is that also the בית הכנסת beit hakeneset
is the entry point for everyone. So, you know, it's sort, you
know, I think it's still again like, I hear, right, I hear
the part like, okay, you got two ways of sort, you know,
two institutions that take the place of the בית המ... בית המקדש,
Beit Ha... Beit HaMikdash, but it's, to me the nagging question still
is, but why would the rabbis give primacy to the one that
is not the one they sort of focus on. So I still
think there's an idea that this is maybe, you know, more something
that everybody, you know, goes to שול, shul, not everybody, you know,
goes to the בית מדרש. Beit Medrash. But it is, yeah, anyway,
I think it raises very interesting questions. Let's just start, we have
to literally end in two minutes. Let's just start the next line
where now ברוך ה' Baruch Hashem a full דף daf behind, we
might have to do two דפים dappim on שבת. Shabbat. אבל מוכרי
תורה לא יקחו ספרים. Aval mochrei Torah lo yikchu sefarim. איבעיא להו.
Ibayya lehu. So here's the question about staying at the same level.
So it says, don't go down, go up. So they ask the
question. מהו למכור ספר ישן ליקח בו חדש. Mahu limkor sefer yashan
likach bo chadash. Can you sell an old ספר תורה sefer Torah
to a different שול? shul? They're going to obviously use it as
a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. I mean, you know, nobody's talking about
changing the status of the שול, shul, you don't talk about changing
the status of ספר תורה. sefer Torah. Okay, but you want to
sell that to a different שול shul and you're going to use
the proceeds to buy a new ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So is
that okay to use the proceeds at an equal level, not going
up, not going down? So here's the question. כיון דלא מעלי ליה
אסור, Keivan dela ma'alei lei assur, since you're not going up it's
forbidden. או דילמא כיון דליכא עילויה עילויה אחרינא, O dilma keivan delika
illuya illuya achrina, since there's nowhere to go up, ספר תורה sefer
Torah is the highest use, שפיר דמי, shapir dami, it's okay. And
based on this question is right... And most ראשונים Rishonim say that
by everything else it seems like you clearly have to go up.
The only question was raised by ספר תורה Sefer Torah that there's
nowhere to go up to, are you allowed to stay at the
same level? The implication being that everything else you can only go
up, you can't stay at the same level. Although that was not
at all clear in the משנה, Mishnah, and although that's a little
bit bizarre. Why can't you stay at the same level? Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara asks the question by the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. תא
שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, אבל מכרו תורה לא יקחו ספרים,
Aval machru Torah lo yikchu sefarim, if you sell תורה, Torah, don't
buy ספרי תנ"ך. Sifrei Tanach. ספרים הוא דלא, Sfarim hu delo, so
you can't go down. התורה בתורה שפיר דמי, HaTorah beTorah shappir dami,
you can use it for a תורה? Torah? But it says no,
מתניתין בדיעבד. Masnitin bediavad. Now, you could have said the other line
in the משנה Mishnah suggested the opposite, but anyway it says no,
our משנה Mishnah is בדיעבד, bediavad, you already sold the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. So now, of course, if you already sold it, there's
nothing left to do except use the proceeds for a ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. כי קמיבעיא לן, Ki kamibaya lan, our question is לכתחילה.
lichatchila. Are לכתחילה lichatchila you allowed to sell it to stay at
the same level? תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, גוללים ספר
תורה במטפחות חומשים, Golelim Sefer Torah bematpachot chumashim, you can wrap a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah with things that were used to wrap חומשים,
chumashim, וחומשים במטפחות נביאים וכתובים, vechumashim bematpachot Neviim u'Ketuvim, and חומשים chumashim
you can wrap with things which were used for נביאים וכתובים. Neviim
u'Ketuvim. אבל לא נביאים וכתובים במטפחות חומשים, Aval lo Neviim u'Ketuvim bematpachot
chumashim, but again, you can't go in the reverse. You can't wrap
נביאים וכתובים Neviim u'Ketuvim things you wrapped חומשים chumashim in, ולא חומשים
במטפחות ספרי תורה. velo chumashim bematpachot Sifrei Torah. קתני מיהת, Katani mihat,
גוללים ספר תורה במטפחות חומשים, Golelim Sefer Torah bematpachot chumashim, that you
can use those from חומשים chumashim to wrap a ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. מטפחות חומשים אין מטפחות ספר תורה לא, Matpachot chumashim in, matpachot
Sefer Torah lo, but you can't take מטפחות matpachot from one ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, let's say, and now use them to wrap a
different ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, which is bizarre, like that that even
would be an issue. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara asks transfer, why
is that transfer, why is that not just using it in the
same way? But anyway, that's the way the גמרא Gemara understood, that
you can't transfer to the same level. So you see that keeping
it at the same level is not acceptable even in the realm
of a ספר תורה Sefer Torah where presumably there's no choice of
going up. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, no,
that's not a proof because look at the end. ולא חומשים במטפחות
ספר תורה, Velo chumashim bematpachot Sefer Torah, it says you can't go
down. הא תורה בתורה שפיר דמי, Ha Torah beTorah shappir dami, to
use a wrap of a תורה Torah for a different תורה, Torah,
that would be okay. This is always the problem. It says you
have to go up, you can't go down. It never addresses the
case of staying at the same level. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה, Ella meha leka lemishma mina, from there
you cannot figure out one or the other way, and we will
have to continue tomorrow to try to figure out about using the
proceeds of a ספר תורה Sefer Torah for another ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. Okay. When you're selling the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, assuming that
you're selling it for something else? What? No, the ספר תורה, Sefer
Torah, that's what I said. The ספר תורה Sefer Torah obviously is
being used as a ספר תורה Sefer Torah by whoever's buying it.
And the question is just what you do with the proceeds. I
gotta go. No, it's not a problem, I just gotta rush. Is
that service available today? Yeah, yeah. I appreciate it when it is.
All right, tomorrow, see you tomorrow, you going? You let me know.
Okay, let me know. All right, I'm going, let me know. Okay,
good. All right, but don't, please don't use that, don't make that
decision. All right.